既然我们已经了解了一次一密，现在来讨论如何利用流密码
Now that we know about the one-time pad,
let's talk about making the one-time pad
来使一次一密变得更加实用。开始之前
more practical using something called the
stream cypher. But before we do that,
让我们快速回顾一下我们进行到哪了。提醒一下大家，
let's do a quick review of where we were.
So let me just remind you that a cypher is
密码系统是定义在一个三元组上的,即密钥空间,明文空间和密文的空间
defined over a triple of sets called a key
space, a message space, and a cypher text
密码算法由一对高效的算法E和D组成
bare space. And a cypher is a pair of
efficient algorithms called E and D; E
E代表加密算法，D代表解密算法。这里唯一需要满足的特性就是
stands for encryption and D stands for
decryption. And the only property. That we
应当满足解密算法是加密算法的逆运算。换句话说
need to satisfy is that decryption is the
opposite of encryption. In other words if
如果我用特定的密钥给消息m加密，解密就得用相同的密钥
I encrypt a message M using a particular
key. And I de-crypt using the same key. I
这样就得到了最初的消息m。上节课我们看到一对弱密码机制
get back the original message. Last time
we looked at a couple of weak cyphers like
例如代换密码和vigonaire密码。我们可以看出它们都很容易
the substitution cypher and the vigonaire
cypher. We showed that all of them can be
被破解以至于你永远不应该用这些密码
easily broken so you should never ever,
ever use those cyphers. Those were just
这些都是历史经验证明,现在我们来看第一个例子,一个更优越的密码体制
for historical reference. And then we
looked at our first exam.ple of a good
称作“一次一密”,让我告诉你一次一密是如何定义的
cypher, namely the one-time pad. So let me
just remind you how the one-time pad is
首先明文空间是一连串的比特码
defined. Basically the message space is
the set of all bit end bit strings. The
密文是一组比特流。同样的，密钥是
cypher text is a set of all bit end bit
strings. And similarly, the key. Is the
N位比特流，并且加密方法是通过简单异或来加密明文。
set of all N bit strings and the way we
encrypt is by a simple exor to encrypt the
我们只用密钥与明文做异或就得到密文。
message we just exor the message in the
key that gives us the cypher text. And
之后对密文解密，只需用再一次做异或
then to decrypt a cypher text, we just do
this x over again and it's easier to show
这很容易看出整个算法过程,这就体现了解密是加密的逆运算
by properties of x over that in fact
decryption is the opposite of encryption.
现在我们讲一下这个定理。实际上，我们证明了
And then we talked about this lemma, in
fact, we proved it, that says that the
一次一密具有很好的保密性,指的是如果你是一个窃听者
one-time pad has perfect secrecy, which
means that if you're just an eavesdropper
且只有一个简单的密文，你将不可能
and you just get to see a single cypher
text, you're not going to be able to
推断出任何有关已经加密的文本的信息。很不幸，我们也说过
deduce any information about the encrypted
plain text. Unfortunately. We also said
香农证明了这个定理。我们称它为坏消息定理，它实际在说
that Shannon proved this lema, we called
it the bad news lema, that basically says
任何一个密码，要想要完全保密必须要有很长的密钥。换句话说
that any cypher that has perfect secrecy
must have really long keys. In other
密钥的长度至少和明文的长度一样
words, the key length must be at least as
long as the length of the message, which
也就意味着这种密码体制不是很实用。因为如果双方
means that the cypher is not particularly
useful. Because if two parties have a way
同意密钥的长度和明文一样长，在某种程度上
to agree on really long keys that are as
long as the message, they, in some sense,
他们可能早已用这种机制传送消息本身了。所以在这堂课上
might as well use that mechanism to
already transmit the message itself. So in
我们将使用一次一密的思想并且使之成为实用的加密方案
this lecture we're going to take the idea
of the one time pad and try to make it
所以，这就是所谓的流密码
into a practical encryption scheme. So
this is called what's called a stream
在流密码中，并不用随机密钥
cypher. So the idea in this dream cypher
is rather than using a totally random key,
实际我们用的是伪随机序列。为了解释它如何工作
we're actually going to use a
pseudo-random key. And to explain how that
我需要定义什么是伪随机生成器-PRG。PRG实际上就是
works, I need to define what is a
pseudo-random generator, PRG. So a PRG,
一个函数,记做种子密钥的生成器g
really, all it is, is just a function,
I'll call it g for generator, that takes a
我们用集合的s次方来表示0,1比特串长度为s
seed, so I'm going to use zero one to the
s to denote all strings of length s, so
这个我们称这个集合为种子空间,他将s比特的种子转化成一个更长的比特串，
this we'll call the seed space. So he
takes an s bit seed and maps it to a much
该串的长度用的n次方来表示。必须满足的是n比s大。
larger string which will denote by zero
one to the n. And the property is that n
换句话说我们输入种子密钥可能仅仅128比特
must be much larger than s. So in other
words, we take a seed that might be only
之后我们把他扩展成更长的可以达到千兆字节长度的输出串
128 bits and we expand it into a much,
much larger output string that could be
这就是伪随机生成器所做的。当然
gigabytes long. That's what this
pseudo-random generator does. And of
目标是首先发生器必须是高效可计算的
course, the goal is that first of all, the
generator is efficiently computable, so
所以对于函数g，应该是一类可计算的高效的算法来计算它
the function g. There should be some sort
of an efficient algorithm that computes
函数必须由一个确定的算法高效计算着。
it. So, efficiently computable by a
deterministic algorithm. It's important to
函数g自身没有随机性,理解这点是很重要的,它是确定性的。
understand that the function g itself has
no more randomness, in it, it's a totally
唯一具有随机性的是种子密钥
deterministic. The only thing that's
random here is the random seed, that's
它被作为函数g的输入。它的另一个特性是输出
given as input to the function g. And the
other property, of course, is that the
看起来是随机的。问题是它看起来是随机的指的是什么？
output. Should look random and the
question is what does it mean to look
这我们将在后面的课程中给出定义，好，假设
random, and that's something we'll define
later on in the lecture. Okay so suppose
我们有一个发生器，那么我们怎样用它生成流密码
we have such a generator, how do we use
that, to build a stream cipher? We the
我们的思路是用种子来作为密钥。短种子被作为秘密密钥，
idea is that we're gonna use the seed, as
our key, so our short seed is gonna be our
然后我们用生成器将种子密钥扩展
secret key. And then we're gonna use the
generator to basically expand the seed
成更长的类随机序列或者伪随机序列
into a much, much larger random looking
sequence, or pseudo random sequence, as
由已知,我们可以得到G(k),之后用它进行异或就像
it's known, so this would be G of K. And then
we are going to X over it just like in the
在一次一密中那样。我们用伪随机序列和明文做异或
one time pad we're going to X over it the
student random sequence with the message
就得到了密文。如果我们想用数学语言来表达
and that's going to give us the cypher
text. Or if we want to write this in math,
那么就用c代表信息经密钥k加密后的密文m，
we'll write C equals the encryption of the
message M with a key K, which is simply
则c定义为m和G(k)的异或。接下来我们要做解密,基本上就是在做
defined as M XOR G of K. And then when we
want to decrypt, basically we do exactly
同样的工作。用密文异或G(k),就像在一次一密中那样，
the same thing. It's basically the cypher
text XOR G of K, just like in the one-time
除了不是与K异或,我们用生成器的输出与K进行异或运算
pad except then instead of XOR-ing with K,
we XOR with the output of the generator
所以第一个要问的问题是为什么这是安全的
applied to K. So the first question to ask
is why is it secure? So, basically you
其实，到目前为止，我们现在只有一个安全概念即完全保密
now, we only have one notion of security
so far, which we called perfect secrecy.
所以让我们看看流密码是否具有完全保密性,记得在
And so let's just quickly ask can a stream
cipher have perfect secrecy. Remember in
流密码中,密钥长度远远比信息的,所以
the stream cipher the key is much, much
shorter than the message. And so, never
流密码是否具有完全保密性,我希望每个人的回答是"不"
the less, can it have perfect secrecy. So
I hope everybody said the answer is, no.
密钥远远比明文的长度短。而我们说
The key is much shorter than the message.
And we said that in a, in a perfectly
在完全保密体制中，密钥必须和明文一样长。因此
secure cypher, the key must be as long as
the mesage. And therefore, it's not
一个流密码要具有完全保密性是不可能的。
possible that a, that a stream cypher
actually has perfect secrecy. So the
所以问题是它为什么又是安全的呢？首先我们需要对安全性给出一个不同的定义
question is, then, well, why is it secure?
First of all we would need a different
才能讨论流密码的安全性。 尤其是
definition of security to argue that
Stream Safe is, is secure and in
安全性取决于我们所使用的特定的生成器
particular, the security property is going
to depend on the specific generator that
实际上，由流密码安全性所给出的私密性定义
we used. So in fact the definition of
privacy that we'll need to argue the
我们将在下一节课中给出。现在让我给你们展示
security of Stream Cipher is we'll see in
the next lecture, but for now let me show
一个特殊的特性。那就是发生器对于安全性的要求必须有一个最小限度
you one particular property. That a
generator must have a minimum property
这个特性被称为不可预测性,所以
needed for security. This property is
called unpredictability. So let's we
让我们暂时假设一个流密码是可预测的，那么
suppose for one second that in fact a
stream cycle is predictable. So, what does
这意味着什么？同样,PRG也是可预测的,意思就是主要这里存在一个i值
that mean? Both the PRG is predictable.
What that means is essentially that there
如果我给出输出的前i位，这个符号
is some pi. Such that if I give you the
first I bits of the outputs. This notation
的意思是函数输出的前i个比特
Bar one to I means look at the first
I-bits of the output of the function.
好的,我给你这个流密码的前i位。这里有一类
Okay, so I give you the first I bits of
the stream. There is some sort of an
可以计算剩余字串的有效算法
algorithm, there's an efficient algorithm
that will compute the rest of the string.
所以我给你前i位,你可以计算出剩余的比特串
Okay, so given the first I bits, you can
compute the remainder of the bits. I claim
如果是这种情况,流密码是不安全的。让我们看看为什
that if this is the case, then the stream
cypher would not be secure. So let's see
假设一个攻击者拦截了一个特定的密文c
why. Suppose an attacker actually
intercepts a particular cypher text, let's
如果是这样，那么我们有一个问题。因为假设
call it c. If this is the case, then in
fact, we have a problem. Because suppose
根据之前获得的信息，攻击者实际上知道的信息开头的部分
that just by some prior knowledge, the
attacker actually knows that the initial
刚好就是一些已知值,例如，我们知道
part of the message happens to be some
known value. For example, we know that in
在一些邮件传输协议中，比如smtp协议--应用在网络中的标准邮件发送协议
the mail protocol, smtp, the standard mail
call used in the internet, you know that
每条信息都以冒号开始。这是每一个敌手都知道的前缀
every message starts with a word from
colon. Well, that would be a prefix that
对网站来说发送的信息必须以冒号开始
the adversary knows. That the site, that
the message must begin with from a colon.
网站能做就是它能够用冒号引出加密的密文
What it could do is it could [inaudible]
the cipher text with the words from colon,
用已知明文的一点前缀引出密文。它能给的只是
with the little prefix of the message that
it actually knows. And what that would
这就能给他一个伪随机序列的前缀，结果就是我将
give it is a prefix of. Of the pseudo
random sequence. And I would learn as a
获得伪随机序列的前缀。但我们知道
result of this, it would learn a prefix of
the pseudo random sequence but then we
一旦知道伪随机序列前缀就可以推测出
know that once it has a prefix of the
pseudo random sequence it can predict the
剩余的序列码并且进一步可以推测出整个信息的剩余部分
remainder of the pseudo random sequence
and that would allow it to then predict
好的，例如如果伪随机序列生成器是
the rest of the message end. Okay, so for
example if the pseudo random generator was
可预测的并给他5个比特之后，每一个用此流密码加密的邮件
predictable given five bits of the pad.
Then every email encrypted using the
被解密，因为攻击者通过推断密码本的前缀
stream cypher would be decryptable
because, again, the attacker knows the
来获取消息的前缀，这样他就能够
prefix of the message from which he
deduces the prefix of the pad, which then
计算出剩余的密码本之后的部分，从而进一步恢复
allows him to compute the rest of the pad,
which then allows him to recover the
整个未加密的文本。好的这就是一个例子,说明了如果一个PRG
entire plain text. Okay, so this is an
example that shows that in fact if a PRG
是可预测的那么它就存在安全问题。因为一个小的前缀
is predictable then already there are
security problems. Because a small prefix
将泄漏整个信息。结果就是,如果我能预测出
would reveal the entire message. As it
turns out, even if I could predict just
输出的一位，如果给我前i位，我能预测出
one bit of the outputs. Even if given, you
know, the first I bits, I can predict the
下一位，再加上第一位。这显然存在一个问题。再解释一遍就是说
next bits, the I plus first bits. Already,
this is a problem. Because that would say
给出信息的前几个字母就可以预测和
that given again, the first couple of
letters in a message can predict, can
和解密，并且恢复出消息的下一位或者下一层，
decrypt essentially, and recover the next
bit of the message, or the next layer of
从而不断重复这个过程。所以说这种可预测的特性告诉我们
the message, and so on. So this
predictability property shows that, you
用于流密码的PRG最好是
know, if we use a PRG that's going to be
used in a stream cypher, it had better be
不可预测的。那么PRG是不可预测的意味着什么呢？接下来让我们更
unpredictable. So what does it mean that a
PRG is unpredictable? So let's define more
准确的阐述PRG的不可预测性有什么意义。我们先来阐述
precisely what it means for a PRG to be
unpredictable. Well first we'll define
PRG的可预测性有什么意义。我们先考虑G是可预测的
more precisely what it means for a PRG to
be predictable. So we say that G is
如果存在一个有效的算法，称为A
predictable, if there exists an efficient
algorithm. Let's call it A and there is
并且存在一个位置i存在于1到N-1之间。基于此，如果
some position. There's a position I
between one and N minus one such that if
我们观察一个随机密钥的概率,如果我生成一个随机密钥
we look at the probability over a random
key. Probability if I generate a random
你们记得，这个记号表示从集合K中选择一个随机密钥
key. You remember, this notation means
choose a random key from the set k. So
所以，这个带r的箭头符号表示从集合K选择随机密钥。基本上，如果我
this arrow with r just means choose a
random key from the set k. Basically, if I
把输出的前缀给这个算法，如果把输出的前I字节给这个算法，
give this algorithm the prefix of the
output, if I give it the first I bytes of
则算法能推测出输出的下一个位的概率
the output, the probability that it's able
to predict the next bit of the outputs,
大于1/2+ε因为一些不可忽略的ε
this probability is greater than half plus
epislon. For some non-negotiable. For some
例如
non-negligible. >> [inaudible]. >> A non
[inaudible], for example, would be
e的值大于1/2^30，比如1/10^9就是不可忽略的
epsilon, which is great than one over two
to the 30. One over a billion, for
我们认为是不可忽略的 这些术语，可忽略和
example, we would consider it not
negligible. So these terms, negligible and
不可忽略的，我们都将在这节课的最后回到这里并且给出更准确的定义
non negligible will come back at the end
of the lecture, and define them more
不过现在让我们凭直觉思考一下不可忽略
precisely. But for now, let's just, stick
with the intuitive notion of what non
意味着什么。它是指对于一个算法，一个发生器来说是可预测的
negligible means. And so this is what it
means, for an algorithm, for a generator
实际，有一些算法可以预测I加第一个比特
to be, predictable. Basically, there is
some algorithm that is able to predict the
甚至共同的前缀，明白了吗？我们说一个算法
I plus first bits, even the mutual prefix,
okay? And then we say that an algorithm,
P或者G是不可预测的。实际，如果它不满足
that a P or G is unpredictable. If in
fact, well, if it's doesn't satisfy the
我们之前定义的特性，那么它就是不可预测的
property that we just defined. In other
words, it is not predictable. But what
但是是什么意思呢，对于不可预测更确切的意思是
does it mean, more precisely for it not to
be predictable. It means that, in fact,
对于i的所有值 不存在有效的对手和
for all positions, for all i there is
no efficient adversary no efficient
有效的算法A,在不可忽略的概率下能预测出i+1位
algorithm A that can predict the i + 1
bit with non negligible probability.
好的，对于所有I这都是成立的，无论我给你怎样的前缀
Excellent. Okay and this has to be true
for all I. So no matter which prefix I
你都不能推测出前缀的后一位
give you, you're not gonna be able to
predict the next bit that follows the
好的，让我们看看一些例子，一个十分简单的例子
prefix. Okay, so let's look at some
examples. Here is a silly, silly example.
假设我给你一个生成器，我的问题是它是否可预测的
Suppose I give you a generator, and I ask
you, is it predictable? Well, this
这个生成器恰巧具有这种特性,这种特性就是如果我把所有输出位进行
generator happens to have the property,
that if I XOR all the bits of the
异或,我总是恰巧得到1。所以,我对所有位进行异或。异或第一位，
outputs, I always happen to get one. Okay,
so I x over all the bits. Bit number one,
异或第二位,异或第三位.如果我对所有位进行异或
x over bit number two, xor  bit number
three. If I x over all those bits, I
恰巧得到1 问题是这是一个可预测的生成器吗？
happen to get one. The question is, is
that a predictable generator? And again, I
再一次,我希望每个人回答"是", 主要是给出输出字节的前n-1位
hope everybody answered yes, that
essentially given the first n minus one
就可以推测出第n位 因为仅仅需要比特值
bits of the outputs, I can predict the nth
bit because it would just be the bits
让它做异或运算使所有位为1。换句话说,我给你们
that's needed to make the x over all the
bits be one. In other words, I give you
除了生成器的比特值中的一个其他的所有值,你就可以推测出生成器的最后一个字节
all but one of the bits of the generator,
you can actually predict the last bit of
既然我们已经明白了PRG必须是不可预测的。我想
the generator. Now that we've seen that
PRGs have to be unpredictable, I just want
提及一下一对永远都不会用于加密的弱伪随机序列生成器（PRGs)
to mention a couple of weak PRGs that
should never ever be used for crypto. This
这是一个非常普遍的错误，我希望你们中没人
is a very common mistake and I just want
to make sure none of you guys make this
犯这样的错误。一个很常见的PRG绝不会被用于加密,这种PRG被称作
mistake. So a very common PRG that should
actually never be used for crypto is
线性同余生成器 我来解释一下什么是线性同余生成器
called a linear congruential generator. So
let me explain what a linear congruential
首先它有一些参量,这里是三个参量,我将它们称作A
generator is. Basically it has parameters.
It has three parameters. I'll call them A,
B,和P。A和B是整数,P是一个素数。生成器定义如下：
B and P. A and B are just integers and P
is a prime. And the generator is defined
假设R0是生成器的种子密钥。然后
as follows, essentially I'll say R zero is
the seed of the generator. And then the
生成随机序列的方法主要有以下
way you generate randomness is basically
you [inaudible] run through the following
这些步骤。计算r[i]=a*r[i-1](mod P)之后输出
steps. You compute a times r of I minus
one plus b modular p. Then you output a
一些位的当前状值，输出i的几位，然后增加i
few bits of the current states, output few
bits of our i. Then, of course, you
并且一遍又一遍的重复。好的，现在你知道这种生成器是怎么进行了。
increment I and you iterate this again and
again and again. Okay? So you can see how
它由一个特殊的种子开始，在每一步
this generator proceeds. It starts with a
particular seed. At every step there is
这种线性转换都作用于种子密钥，之后输出部分位
this leaner transformation that's being
applied to the seed. And then you output a
的当前状态，并且不断地重复这个过程。
few bits of the current state and then you
do that again and again and again and
很不幸,即使这样,这个生成器在某种程度上也具有良好的
again. Unfortunately even though this
generator has good statistical properties
统计特性。例如，它输出的0的个数和输出中
in the sense that, for example, the number
of zeroes it outputs is likely going to be
1的个数相似等等，对于这一点，你可以探讨各种良好的统计
similar to the number of ones and so on;
it has, you can actually argue all sorts
特性。然而它是一个非常容易预测的生成器
of nice statistical properties about this,
nevertheless it is a very easy generator
实际是绝不会被应用的。实际上，给定一些
to predict. And in fact should never ever
be used. In fact, just given a few
输出样本很容易预测剩余序列
outputs, a few output samples, it's easy
to predict the remainder of the sequence.
导致这种生成器将不会被应用。另一个例子是
And as a result, this generator should
never ever be used. Another example is a
一个随机数生成器与线性同余生成器关系十分密切。
random number generator that is very
closely related to the linear congruential
这是一个运用于glibc的随机数生成器,glibc是一个很常见的库
generator. This is a random number
generator implemented in glibc, very
你能发现，我刚刚把定义写了出来
common library. That you can see. I just
wrote down the definition here. You can
就可以看出,每次循环输出几个比特，并且每一步都
see that is basically outputs a few bits
at every ideration and it just does this
做这样简单的线性变换。再次强调,这是一个非常简单的可预测的生成器
simple linear transformation at every
step. Again, this is a very easy generator
并且绝不应该应用于加密。所以第一节课我想强调
to predict and should never ever be used
for crypto. And so the lesson I want to
永远不要使用内置的glibc库函数。对于加密来说
emphasize here is never ever use the
built-in glibc function random. For crypto,
从容易预测的意义来看，它并不会减少密码随机性
because it doesn't reduce,
cryptographic randomness, in the sense
实际上，Kerberos版本4系统就使用了随机数生成器
that it is easy to predict. And, in fact,
systems like Kerberos version four have
并深受此害。请你们不要犯这样的错误。
used random and, have been bitten by that.
So, please don't make that mistake
在下节课我们将会讨论如何实现安全的随机数生成器。
yourself. We will talk about how to do
secure random number generation actually in
在总结这节课之前我想给出一些关于
the next lecture. Before we conclude this
lecture I just want to give a little bit
有关可忽略和不可忽略的概念的细节。
more detail about these concepts of
negligible and non-negligible values, so
密码界不同的派别对这些概念有不同的定义
different communities in crypto actually
define these concepts differently, for
对于实习者来说，这些可忽略和不可忽略的术语仅是
practitioners basically these the term
negligible and non-negligible,
被用在定义中的特殊的词。举个例子来说，
are just, particular scalers that are used in the
definition. So, for example, a
一个实习者会说如果一个值大于1/10^9,
practitioner would say, that if a value is
more than one over, one over a billion,
或者大于1/2^30我们就认为这个值不能忽略
one over two to the 30, we say that the
value is non-negligible. The reason is,
原因就在于，因为如果你恰巧用一个密钥来加密
the reason that's so, is, because if you
happen to use a key, for example, for, for
一个GB级别大小的数据。GB级别大小的数据大概就在2^30
encrypting a gigabyte of data, a gigabyte
of data is about two to the 30 or maybe
到2^32字节之间。一个以1/2^30的概率发生的事件
even two to the 32 bytes. Then an event
that happens with the probability one over
更可能出现在生成了GB大小的数据之后。那么既然
two to the thirty will likely happen after
about a gigabyte of data. So since a
GB级别大小的数据对于一个特定的密钥来说是可能的话，那么这个事件就很有可能
gigabyte of data is within reason for a
particular key, this event is likely to
发生。因此1/2^30就是不可忽略的。另一方面
happen. Therefore one over two to the
thirty is non-negligible. On the other
我们来考虑1/2^80，这是一个更小概率的事件
hand, we'll say that one over two to the
eighty. Which is much, much, much smaller
这种事件发生的概率对于
is an event, an event that happens with
this probability is an event that's
密钥的生命期来说基本是不会发生的。于是我们说
actually not going to happen over the life
of the key. And therefore we'll say that
这是可忽略的事件，如上所述，这些有关忽略和不可忽略的实际的定义
that's a negligible event. As it turns
out, these practical definitions of
是相当有问题的。我们通过例子来看看为什么说它有问题？
negligible and non-negligible are quite
problematic and we'll see examples of why
为什么说它有问题？实际上在许多严密的密码学理论中，
they're problematic later on. So in fact
in the more rigerous theory of
忽略性与不可忽略性的定义是有些不同的。
cryptography, the definition of negligible
and non-negligible are somewhat different.
实际上，我们在讨论一个事件的概率时，
And in fact, when we talk about the
probability of an event, we don't talk
我们并不去讨论这些概率的数值，反而我们将概率作为
about these probabilities as scalers, but
rather we talk about them as functions of
函数安全参数来讨论。让我来解释这是什么意思。这些函数
a security parameter. So let me explain
what that means. So these functions,
本质上是映射输出的函数。正实数值是可能作为概率值的
essentially, are functions that map, that
outputs, positive real values. So, are non
非负实数.但是它们是在非负整数集上工作的函数。
negative real values that are supposedly
probabilities. But they're functions that
那么对于一个函数来说，不可忽略意味着什么？
act on non negative integers, okay? So,
what does it mean for a function to be
它是指函数通常比一些无限多项式大
non-negligible? What it means is that the
function is bigger than some polynomial
换句话说，对于无限的取值，函数值比
infinitely often. In other words, for
many, for infinitely many values, the
1/poly大，明白吗？我把准确
function is bigger than some, one over
polynomial, okay? So I wrote the exact
的定义写在这里。我们来看个例子，如果一个数较大
definition here, and we'll see an example,
in just a minute. Okay? So if something is
它通常应大于1/poly，那么我们就说这个值是不可忽略的
bigger, is often bigger than one of that
polynomial, we'll say that it's non-negligible.
但是，如果存在数值小于所有多项式的值，那么
However, if something is
smaller than all polynomials, then we'll
我们认为他是可以忽略的。就说到这，通常对任何次的
say that it's negligible. So, what this
says here, basically, for any degree
多项式，对所有的d值，存在一些下限λd
polynomial, for all d, there exists some
lower bound lambda-d such as, for all
所有λ都大于λd，函数小于1/poly。
lambda bigger than this lambda-d, the
function is smaller than one over the
这些都在说如果函数小于多项式的每一部分就认为他可以忽略
polynomial. So all this says is that the
function is negligible if it's less than
换句话说就是存在足够大且小于1/λd的λ。
all polynomial fractions. In other words, is
less than one over lambda-d for
让我们看一些例子之后就会发现这些
sufficiently large lambda. So let's look
at some examples. And we'll see
这些忽略和不可忽略的概念的应用。但是我
applications of these negligible and
non-negligible concepts later on. But I
仅想使大家更清楚怎样才能严密地发现这些概念。
just want to make, wanted to make it clear
that this is how you would rigorously find
通常，不论小于1/poly或者大于1/poly
these concepts. Basically either smaller
than one over poly or bigger than one over
都是可忽略的 否则就是不可忽略的。让我们看一些例子
poly, one would be negligible, the
other would be non-negligible. Let's look
例如，一个函数以λ的指数形式下降
at some examples. So, for example, a
function that drops exponentially in
明显是可忽略的，因为对任何一个常量d存在一个有效很大的λ
lambda clearly would be negligible because
for any constant d there is a sufficiently
例如1/2^λ小于1/λ^d
large, large lambda. Such as one over two
to the lambda is less than one over lambda
好的明显这个值小于所有的多项式。这个函数，比如
to the d. Okay. So this is clearly less
than all polynomials. Over the function,
1/λ^1000这个函数增长得非常慢，
say, one over lambda to a thousand, right.
This is a function that grows very, very,
几乎不增长，然而这个函数
very slowly. It barely ever moves.
Nevertheless, this function is
是不可忽略的因为如果我设d等于10000 明显这个函数
non-negligible because if I set d to be
10,000, then clearly this function is
大于1/λ^10000，所以这个函数大于
bigger than one over lambda to the 10,000.
And so this function is bigger than some
部分多项式，让我们看一个费解且巧妙的例子
polynomial fraction. And lets look at a
confusing example, just to be tricky. What
你怎么认为？我有一个函数，当λ是奇数时，函数恰巧呈指数减小
do you think? Suppose I have a function that for
an odd lambda it happens to be exponentially small,
当λ是偶数时，函数恰好呈多式形式减小。那么这是一个可忽略的还是
for even lambda, it happens to be
polynomially small. Is this a negligible or
不可忽略的函数呢？按照我们的定义这个函数是不可忽略的
non-negligible function? Well, by our
definition this would a non-negligible
由直觉判断如果一个函数以多项式形式减小，
function. And the intuition is, if a
function happens to be only polynomially
那么通常意味着以这个概率发生的事件
small, very often, that actually means
that this event, you know, an event
在实际的密码系统中已经是很大的事件了，
that happens with this probability, is
already too large to be used in a real
所以，主要需要记住的点是这些术语
cryptosystem. Okay, so, the main points to
remember here, are that these terms,
分别对应着小于多项式或者大于多项式，
basically, correspond to less than
polynomial or more than polynomial, but
贯穿这门课程，我们大多数情况用忽略性表示小于一个指数。
throughout the course, we'll mostly use
negligible to mean less than, than an
不可忽略表示小于1/poly，所以现在可以看到
exponential. And non-negligible to mean,
less than one over polynomial. So now we
把一次一密转化为实用性密码的核心思想,这里的实用性密码
saw the core idea for converting the one
time pad into a practical cipher. And I
就是流密码。在下节课中我们将学习
mean, the stream cipher. And then, in the
next lecture, we're gonna see how to
如何讨论一个流密码是否是真的安全的。这就需要
actually argue that the stream cipher is
actually secure. That's gonna require a
对安全性进行全新的定义，因为完全安全对于密码说还不够好
new definition of security, since perfect
secrecy is not good enough here, and we
并且我们将在下一节课中看到。
will see that in the next lecture.